Finding Aid for Edward Martin collection, 1852-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Edward Martin collection 1852-2004
Martin, Edward, collector.
1 oversize folders
3 oversize volumes
14 linear feet (in 22 boxes)
0727 Aa 2; UAl
Collector of materials documenting Michigan Polish-American individuals and organizations, especially in Detroit and Hamtramck. Included are records of the Detroit Board of Water Commissioners, the Polish Army Veterans Association, and the Polish Sea League. The collection also contains photographs from various Polish photography studios in Detroit and Michigan, including portraits and topical photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Materials were received from Dr. Edward Martin (donor no. 9820 ) in 2006-2009.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Dr. Edward Martin, a Detroit and Flint, Michigan physician, is a collector of materials largely documenting the activities of Polish American individuals and organizations in the Detroit area.
The Edward Martin collection consists of papers and photographs, accumulated from various sources, relate to Detroit organizations and individuals. Except for a small series of Detroit Board of Water Commissioners documents, the collection concerns Michigan's Polish-American community and the activities of Polish-American organization, including the Polish Army Veterans Association and the Polish Sea League. Much of the collection consists of photographic portraits from studios catering to the Polish-American community in Detroit and Hamtramck.
The collection consists of seven series: Detroit Board of Water Commissioners, Polish Army Veterans Association, Polish Sea League, Printed Polish Materials, Waclaw S. Jakubowski papers, Miscellaneous, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Detroit (Mich.). Board of Water Commissioners.; Stowarzyszenie Weteranów Armii Polskiej w Ameryce.; Liga Morska w Ameryce.; American Legion. Christian Post no. 278 (Detroit, Mich.); Cunningham's Drug Stores (Mich.); Polish Legion of American Veterans.; Polish National Alliance of the United States of North America.; Mariavite Old Catholic Church (Wyandotte, Mich.); St. Albertus Church (Detroit, Mich.); St. Bartholomew Parish (Detroit, Mich.); Veterans of Foreign Wars of the United States. Gordon R. Bennett Post 1452 (Clio, Mich.); Drugs--Prescribing--Michigan--Clio.; Poletown (Detroit, Mich.); Polish Americans--Michigan.; Water-supply--Michigan--Detroit.; Veterans--Poland.; Veterans--Michigan--Detroit.; Drugstores--Michigan.; Photographers--Michigan.; Clio (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
African Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Bethlehem Steel Company.; Clarke, Herbert L. (Herbert Lincoln), 1867-1945.; Stowarzyszenie Weteranów Armii Polskiej w Ameryce.; Commercial facilities--Michigan--Detroit.; Furniture stores--Michigan--Detroit.; Pipes (Conduits)--Michigan--Detroit.; Clergy--Michigan--Detroit.; Weddings.; Military officers.; Church schools--Michigan--Detroit.; Mackinac Island (Mich.); Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; Polish Americans--Michigan.
Contributors:
Jakubowski, Waclaw S.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Detroit Board of Water Commissioners 1852-1963
  The Detroit Board of Water Commissioners series (0.4 linear feet, 1852-1963) primarily contains business correspondence (mostly incoming) of the Detroit Board of Water Commissioners. Photographs of offices and staff as well as pipes, machinery and workers can also be found in this series.
  - Correspondence
    - 1852 (Box 1)
    - 1861 (Box 1)
    - 1862 (Box 1)
    - 1864 (Box 1)
    - 1868 (Box 1)
    - 1869, 1 volumes (Box 1)
    - 1871-1972, 1 volumes (Box 1)
    - 1874 (Box 1)
    - 1875 (Box 1)
    - 1898 (Box 1)
    - 1899 (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Offices and staff 1963 (Box 1)
    - Pipes, machinery, and workers 1940, 1 volumes (Box 1)
- Polish Army Veterans' Association of America 1946-1984
  (includes district no. 6, Detroit, Mich)
  The Polish Army Veterans' Association series (1.5 linear foot, 1946-1984) includes minutes, correspondence, financial records, membership lists, convention materials, and a photograph primarily documenting the Association's District no. 6 in Detroit.
  - Administration
    - Audit Committee minutes 1981-1984 (Box 1)
    - Constitutions and bylaws (national) 1946-1955 (Box 1)
    - Dockets (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee minute book 1966-1972, 1 volumes (Box 1)
    - Financial reports and budget-related 1957 (Box 1)
    - Leadership lists 1960-1964 (Box 1)
    - Meeting minutes
      - 1959-1960 (Box 1)
      - 1967-1968 (includes correspondence) (Box 1)
    - Membership forms (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
  - Conventions
    - 29th- 1958 (Box 1)
    - 30th- 1959 (Box 1)
    - 33rd- 1962 (Box 1)
    - 34th- 1963 (Box 1)
    - 53rd- 1982 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1958 (relating to veteran financial assistance) (Box 1)
    - 1958-1959 (Box 1)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 1)
    - 1962-1963 (incoming and outgoing), 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 2)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 2)
      (located with meeting minutes in box 1)
    - 1972
      - General (Box 2)
      - Re: sales tax (Box 2)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 2)
  - Photograph (Box 2)
    See also oversize folder
  - Polish Army Veterans Home (Box 2)
  - Protocols, membership records, financial materials, photographs, etc., 0.4 linear feet (Box 2)
    (unprocessed)
- Polish Sea League of America (Liga Morska) 1936-1983
  (includes Flint, Mich. chapter)
  The Polish Sea League series (0.25 linear feet, 1936-1983) contains minutes, financial records, and other miscellaneous administrative material primarily relating to the Flint, Michigan Chapter of the Polish Sea League.
  - Administrative (includes histories, membership lists, minutes) (Box 12)
  - Convention, 15th 1983 (Box 12)
  - Ledger 1936-1948, 1 volumes (Box 12)
  - Minutes 1936-1977, 2 volumes (Box 12)
  - Newsletter (Morze), 1963-1976, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Programs (conventions, anniversaries, etc.) 1967-1982 (Box 12)
- Printed Polish materials (local and national) 1932-2004
  The Printed Polish Materials series (0.25 linear feet, 1932-2004) consists of programs, invitations, newsletters, advertisements and other printed material relating to Polish organizations and activities, both locally (in Detroit, Hamtramck, and Wyandotte) and nationally.
  - Dance programs and announcements circa 1934-1938 (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
    (includes Polish American calendar, Polish dance album (music), handbook for citizenship and clipping)
  - Organizations
    - Miscellaneous 1960-2004 (Box 12)
    - Polish Legion of American Veterans 1958-1995 (Box 12)
    - Polish National Alliance 1980-1988 (Box 12)
  - Religious (includes churches)
    - Miscellaneous 1941-1994 (Box 12)
    - Mariavite Old Catholic Church (Wyandotte, Mich.) (Box 12)
    - St. Albertus Church (Detroit, Mich.) (Box 12)
    - St. Bartholomew Parish (Detroit, Mich.) (Box 12)
  - Advertisements 1932, undated (Box 12)
- Waclaw S. Jakubowski papers
  The Waclaw S. Jakubowski papers (1 linear foot and 1 oversize volume) consists of collected material, mainly clippings, relating to the "Poletown" area of Detroit and to his activities with the Konrad Club (named for the writer Joseph Conrad. The clippings date from the 1930s and are from Polish language newspapers.
  - Clippings and other materials relating to the "Poletown" community in Detroit 1930s (Box 13)
  - Scrapbook of clippings regarding in part the Konrad Club (of which Jakubowski was president) (Volume 1)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous (5.5 linear feet and 2 oversize volumes) series includes scrapbooks, photograph albums, letters, and other materials. One scrapbook includes photographs, programs, and correspondence of the American Legion Christian Post no. 278 in Detroit. Two of the albums contain photographs, programs, and other materials of Post 1452, Veterans of Foreign Wars, Clio, Michigan. In addition, there is a scrapbook containing clippings of advertisements from 1945 to 1947 of the Cunningham's Drug Store, a chain of drug stores that operated principally in Detroit and Southeastern Michigan.
  - Clio, Michigan pharmacy Prescription slips (Box 14)
  - Photograph albums / Scrapbooks of Post 1452 Veterans of Foreign Wars, Clio, Michigan, 2 volumes (Box 15)
  - Collected Polonia, drawn from different sources, 2 folders; 3 volumes (Box 15)
    (include photographs)
  - Photograph album with some invitations of Viola Owings (Detroit African American resident) and her family, 1942-1943 (Box 16)
  - Scrapbook
    - Polish language newspaper clippings, 2 volumes (Box 16)
      (provenance unknown)
    - American Legion. Christian Post no. 278 (Detroit, Mich.) circa 1948-1965 (Volume 2)
    - Cunningham's Drug Store 1945-1947 (Volume 3)
      (include full-page advertisements used in various Michigan newspapers)
  - Polish-American marriage certificates, professional registration certificates, diplomas, etc. (Box 17)
  - Political, commercial, and special event posters (Box 17)
  - Resolutions, certificate of parole, etc. (Box 17)
  - L.C. Minor family correspondence 1945, 1958-1972 (Box 22)
  - Edmund Palka papers undated, 1953-1998 (Box 22)
    (active in First Catholic Slovak Union)
  - Ship's logs: Peace II, Logs 1970-1971 seasons, 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 22)
- Photographs, 1900s-1970s
  The Photographs (6 linear feet in 13 boxes, ca. 1880s-1970s and undated) are from Polish photography studios (mainly in Detroit), Michigan. They consist primarily of wedding portraits and confirmation photographs. Also included is a photograph album of Nicholas Lubinski of Detroit, Michigan. This album includes family photographs, largely undated, of weddings, vacations, and special occasions, ca. 1920-1950s. There are also a few topical photographs of businesses, leisure time activities, African American life, etc.
  - Polish photography studios and other Michigan studios (Detroit, Michigan unless indicated otherwise)
    - Agdan Photographic (Box 3)
    - Agdanowski (Bay City, Mich.) (Box 3)
    - Ballaun Art Studio, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Ballaun & Prusinski (Box 3)
    - Bonish Studio (Box 3)
    - Borg (Box 3)
    - Central Art Studio (Box 4)
    - Chamberlain (Box 4)
    - Classic Studio (Box 4)
    - Cornell Studios (Box 4)
    - M. Derkach (Hamtramck, Mich.) (Box 4)
    - F. A. Drukteinis (Box 4)
    - M. Dusqa & Co. Art Studio (Box 4)
    - Dworshak (city unknown) (Box 4)
    - Eross Studio (Hamtramck, Mich.) (Box 4)
    - Fashion Foto Studio (Box 4)
    - Frank's Harper Studio (Box 4)
    - Genca Studio, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Gilbert Studio (Box 4)
    - Golden Set Studio (Box 5)
    - Grygiel Studio (Box 5)
    - Harbican Studio (Box 5)
    - Hinkston Studio (Box 5)
    - Hoffman Studio, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - W. Jakubowski (Box 5)
    - Litynski Bros. (Box 5)
    - Litynski-Jakubowski (Box 5)
    - Martin Studio (Box 6)
    - Matusiewicz Studio (Box 6)
    - A. Mazur Studio (Box 6)
    - Metropolitan Art Studio (Box 6)
    - Modernistic Photo Studio (Box 6)
    - New Chene (Box 6)
    - L. B. Nowierski (Box 6)
    - S.G. Pasternacki & Co. (Box 6)
    - P. Pieronek (Box 6)
    - Pieronek Studio (Hamtramck, Mich.) (Box 6)
    - F. G. Poli (Box 6)
    - Robinson Studio (Box 6)
    - Rochowiak (Box 7)
    - S. A. Rochowiak (Box 7)
    - Peter Rush Studio (Box 7)
    - Smart Set Studio, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - J. Somheil (Wyandotte, Mich.) (Box 8)
    - Jos. Sowinski, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - D.D. Spellman (Box 8)
    - Sutherland Studio (Pontiac, Mich.) (Box 8)
    - Bill Williams (Royal Oak, Mich.) (Box 8)
    - Wojnicki Bros. (Hamtramck, Mich.) (Box 8)
    - F. Ziawinski, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Joseph Ziawinski (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous Detroit studios, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous Michigan studios, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Topical
    - African Americans (Box 10)
    - Buildings/views
      - General (Box 10)
      - Wedding trip, 1 volumes (Box 10)
        (includes views of Mackinac Island)
    - Businesses/commercial (Box 10)
      (include barber shop and men's clothing store, ca. 1920s)
    - Drawings (Seltzer drawings) (Box 10)
    - Education/schools (Box 10)
    - Ethnic (Box 10)
    - Government (Box 10)
    - Leisure (Box 10)
    - Military (Box 10)
    - People
      - Berger (Box 11)
      - Groups (Box 11)
      - Individuals (Box 11)
    - Religious, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Polish-American wedding photographs, communions, other events (Box 18)
    - "Farmhouse Restaurant" photographs (Box 18)
    - Photographs of homes designed by Hugh Keyes, architect; include Edward Macauley home in Grosse Pointe Farms and home of Mrs. Morse Rohnert; also drawings of homes of John S. Bugas and John W. Stroh (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous group and high school and college class photographs; include Michigan College of Medicine and Surgery, class of 1899 (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous panoramic group photos, 1 folders
      - Young Democratic Clubs of Wayne County July 1936 (Box 18)
      - Polish Army Veterans Association 1928 (Box 18)
      - Polish National Alliance 1924 (Box 18)
      - Banquet in honor General Haller 1923 (Box 18)
  - Nicholas Lubinski
    - Photograph album of Detroit, Michigan, 7 envelopes (Box 19)
    - Lubinski family wedding album (Box 19)
    - Album of wedding at St. Florian in Hamtramck, Michigan (Box 19)
    - Album of vacations and family snapshots (Box 19)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Frank Murphy, Irene Murphy, Sharon Murphy 1949, undated, 1940s-1950s (Box 20)
    - Bethlehem Steel Company executives 1916, circa 1920, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Portraits, non-Michigan photographers circa 1880-1910 (Box 20)
    - Child in casket circa 1900 (Box 20)
    - Group photos, unidentified (Box 20)
    - Individual portraits, unidentified, also couples (Box 20)
    - Portrait: Charles L. Stevens (M.E. Grand High Priest) 1902 (Box 20)
    - Portrait: Herbert L. Clarke (cornetist) circa 1910 (Box 20)
    - Store front: Jas. Fitzsimons & Co., furniture sales, 59 Michigan Ave., Detroit, Mich. 1894 (Box 20)
    - Church interior, unidentified (Box 20)
    - Family album, unidentified (Box 20)
    - Snapshots, unidentified, 2 envelopes (Box 20)
    - Miscellaneous: include home, business district, etc. (Box 20)
    - Album containing cards and clippings with religious images (Box 21)
    - Albums of photographs and other materials of the Baughman family of Muskegon, Michigan (Box 21)
  - Group photos
    (in oversize UAl folder)
    - Grand Carniolian Slovenian Catholic Union, 24th General Convention 1958 (Folder 1)
    - Frederick A. Stratemeyer Class 448 Members, Detroit Consistory April 1945 (Folder 1)
    - Detroit Central High School class photo 1910 published (Folder 1)